Now that you've understood some of the basic principles
of normalcytic anemias, we're now going to apply
those principles to discuss some of the specific diseases
in these categories.
The way I've divided this in your text is to talk about
normalcytic anemias with predominant extravascular hemolysis,
and then we'll talk about normalcytic anemias
with predominant intravascular hemolysis,
and then we'll finally talk about underproduction anemias.
It's important to note here that I used the word
predominant to remind you that these are not absolute.
In some diseases in which there is mostly
extravascular hemolysis, there will be some degree
of intravascular hemolysis often, and so we don't want
to be absolute in the way we think about these,
and I'll hope to point that out to you as we move forward
because examiners also like to play on this notion
that these divisions are not absolute.
I'll highlight that a little later in our discussion as well.
So the first of the disorders that we're going to discuss
is hereditary spherocytosis, and perhaps it's easiest
if I just explain to you via an image before we actually
move forward.
Recall that the red blood cell has a shape which is specialized,
which gives it a biconcave disc, and this red blood cell,
in order to be able to maintain the shape,
has a cytoskeleton that assists in maintaining the shape.
The cytoskeleton is tethered to the cell membrane,
which then allows for the cytoskeleton to perform the function
of maintaining the shape.
In hereditary spherocytosis, the problem is that the tethering
molecules between the cytoskeleton and the cell membrane
are disrupted.
It's an inherited defect, actually.
And this results in small little blebs of membrane coming off
of the red blood cell.
These little blebs are then removed by the spleen when the red blood
cell moves through the spleen.
And over time, as you begin to remove membrane, you lose the ability
to push the membrane in here and push the membrane in here.
And so instead, what happens is the cell becomes spherocytic like this.
And that's hereditary spherocytosis.
So with that in mind, let's go back and read the slide.
Hereditary spherocytosis is an inherited defect of the red blood
cell cytoskeletal membrane tethering proteins.
And the most common examples of these proteins that tend to be involved
in this disease include spectrin, ankerin, and band 3.1.
These are common tethering proteins that allow connection
between the cytoskeleton and the membrane.
Now, because of this, membrane blebs are lost over time,
as I've already illustrated.
The loss of membranes renders the cells round, i.e. spherocytes,
instead of disc-shaped.
This is what the cells look like.
Notice that there is a loss of the central pallor.
And the loss of central pallor is due to the fact that we no longer
have the biconcave shape to the red blood cell.
At the same time, notice that there is a range in the size of the cells.
And the range in the size of the cells is due to the fact that,
remember I told you that when you have this red blood cell, like this,
you're losing a little bit of membrane, and then lose a little bit more membrane,
and then lose more membrane, and more membrane.
And so over time, what's happening is that cells keep losing membrane.
So the oldest cells will have lost the most membrane,
and the youngest cells will have lost the least membrane.
But this is going to create a high RDW,
a high red blood cell distribution width,
i.e. there will be some smaller cells and some larger cells.
And I don't think that's hard to remember
if you understand the basic pathology behind this disease.
In the end, once you get spherocytes that are very small,
they'll be less able to maneuver through the spleen.
And when they're less able to maneuver through the spleen,
they'll be consumed by the spleen, which will then cause the anemia.
Otherwise stated, there really is no problem with having spherocytes.
The real problem is the fact that eventually the spherocytes
will become less able to maneuver through the spleen.
And again, so the spleen will consume them.
Some of the clinical and laboratory features.
They include spherocytes with a loss of central pallor.
I've already shown you that.
An increased RDW.
I've already explained that.
And an increased MCHC.
What's MCHC?
The mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration.
As you begin to shrink down the cell,
the cytoplasm remains about the same.
And so the hemoglobin gets more concentrated within that cell.
And that is measured by the mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration.
It really is probably, for your purposes,
the only disease where you're actually going to see an increased MCHC.
The only other example I can think of would be autoimmune anemia.
But in autoimmune anemia, as I'm going to show you later,
you have a very similar process going on.
And again, you also get the production of spherocytes.
But we'll talk about that in a few minutes.
In addition, patients are going to have splenomegaly.
Why do they have splenomegaly?
Because the spleen is where the consumption of the spherocytes is occurring.
It's important to note, and examiners like to ask you,
that this is a work hypertrophy.
So that the macrophages of the spleen will undergo hypertrophy
as they begin to eat away at these red blood cells.
Patients will also develop jaundice with an unconjugated bilirubin.
And there will be an increased risk for bilirubin gallstones.
If you recall from my previous lecture,
the jaundice is very easy to understand.
As the spleen is eating away at the red blood cells,
it will eventually have to put out unconjugated bilirubin.
That unconjugated bilirubin will overwhelm the liver's ability to conjugate,
and so increased unconjugated bilirubin will be floating around in the blood,
hence the jaundice.
Over time, you're going to conjugate all of that bilirubin by the liver,
and the liver will throw it into the gallbladder,
and that's going to result in a very high concentration of bilirubin in the gallbladder,
increasing the risk for bilirubin gallstones.
These patients will also have an increased risk for aplastic crisis
with parvovirus B19 infection.
We've already covered this, but again,
patients who have limited reserve in their bone marrow
are very susceptible to becoming symptomatic
were they to get a parvovirus B19 infection.
And again, high yield for examinations.
Parvovirus B19 infects the erythroid precursors.
The diagnosis of hereditary spherocytosis occurs by the osmotic fragility test.
And the idea here is that if you have a red blood cell
that has its normal biconcave shape to it,
and you introduce this red blood cell into a hypotonic solution,
water will come into the cell.
And when water comes into the cell,
there is some room for this cell to expand here and here
because there's an extra membrane pushed in here
that can actually expand out both ways before the cell will burst.
So the normal cell is relatively resistant to a hypotonic solution.
However, if you actually had a spherocyte,
the spherocyte has no extra membrane because the membrane's been removed.
And so were this cell to be placed in a hypotonic solution,
water would come in and that would cause the cell to burst very easily.
So this cell is fragile in a hypotonic solution.
And that's the osmotic fragility test.
There is an increased fragility in hypotonic solution.
The treatment for this disease is splenectomy, and that makes sense.
Why?
Because really the problem was in the spleen.
The spleen was where the red blood cells were being eaten.
I told you there's no problem with having spherocytes.
The problem is that the spleen eats the spherocytes,
which then creates the anemia.
So if we treat with splenectomy, the anemia will go away.
The spherocytes will persist.
Why will the spherocytes persist?
Because the cells continue to have a problem with membrane blubbing,
and the cells will still go through some areas of the reticuloendothelial system,
for example, in the liver and in the lymph nodes.
And so some membrane will be removed by the reticuloendothelial system.
However, the anemia will resolve.
And then finally, the other finding is that we'll begin to see howl-jolly bodies on the blood smear.
This requires a little bit of explanation.
Remember that when a red blood cell is born, the red blood cell's nucleus is removed,
and the vast majority of time the nucleus is completely removed.
However, on occasion, there can be a red blood cell in which there is a fragment of nuclear material
that did not get removed.
It is the job of the spleen to go in and to remove that extra fragment of nuclear material.
Basically, if the spleen sees anything abnormal with the red blood cell,
it tends to remove it or to remove the red blood cell completely.
So normally, the spleen would remove little fragments of DNA that might be present in a rare cell or so.
However, in the case of hereditary spherocytosis,
if the patient has undergone splenectomy, the spleen will still not be present.
And therefore, these little fragments of DNA that normally would be removed by the spleen
will remain in the red blood cell.
And that's called a Howell-jolly body, and this is a classic image of a Howell-jolly body.
Again, it indicates splenic dysfunction.
The next of the normalcytic anemias in which there is predominantly extravascular hemolysis
is sickle cell anemia.
In sickle cell anemia, the patients have an autosomal recessive mutation
in the beta chain of hemoglobin such that the normal glutamic acid,
which is hydrophilic, gets replaced with valine, which is hydrophobic.
So it's a single amino acid chain that results in this disease,
and that's called sickle cell anemia.
The gene for this disease is carried by 10% of people of African descent,
and that's because it likely protects against falciparum malaria.
And this is a theme that we've already covered as we've gone through this particular chapter.
When patients have two abnormally mutated beta chains, that's called sickle cell disease,
and it results in greater than 90% production of hemoglobin S.
Here's the idea.
We know that we have two beta genes.
So here's beta gene 1, and here's beta gene 2.
Imagine if this is beta gene that is the sickle mutation,
and this beta gene also has a sickle mutation,
then when this beta gene produces beta, you'll get beta 2 dimers,
and when this beta gene produces beta, we'll get beta 2 dimers,
and of course, this will dimerize with alpha 2, and also with alpha 2.
But in both cases, this is beta S.
So when you have alpha 2, beta 2, and it's a beta S,
this equals hemoglobin S, and this also equals hemoglobin S.
So the primary hemoglobin that's going to be produced in these patients
is going to be hemoglobin S,
and that's why we say it results in greater than 90% hemoglobin S in the red blood cells.
Now what's the problem with hemoglobin S?
It preliminers when it's deoxygenated,
and that's important to understand,
that when these cells are deoxygenated or placed under certain stresses,
for example, hypoxemia, dehydration, acidosis,
all of these circumstances will result in polymerization of the hemoglobin,
which then is going to allow the hemoglobin molecules to aggregate into needle-like structures,
which is then going to cause the cells to take on a banana shape or a sickle shape.
Important to note for examinations that this is a polymerization.
It is not a covalent bonding.
It's a polymerization, and it is reversible.
This is what the sickle cells look like.
They kind of take on this banana shape,
and again, this is due to the polymerization of the hemoglobin S.
The circumstances in which we would see an increased risk of polymerization of the hemoglobin
would be in hypoxemia.
So when the hemoglobin is deoxygenated,
there'll be an increased risk of sickling.
In dehydration, there's an increased risk of sickling.
And in acidosis, there's an increased risk of sickling.
So these are the three driving factors for sickling.
One of the protective factors against sickling is hemoglobin F.
If hemoglobin F is present, it protects against sickling.
This is important because there are two derivative principles
that are derived from this general idea.
Number one, this helps to explain why patients with sickle cell anemia
don't present until about six months of birth.
For the first few months after birth,
the predominant hemoglobin remains hemoglobin F from the fetus.
And so that high hemoglobin F during the first few months of life
actually protects against sickling.
And these patients classically will present at about six months of age.
Another important principle that we can derive from this idea of hemoglobin F
protecting against sickling helps to explain
why treatment with hydroxyurea is beneficial.
Hydroxyurea actually increases the levels of hemoglobin F.
We don't know why, but that's what it does.
And that also helps to protect against sickling.
Now when blood cells with hemoglobin S go through the circulation,
they will actually sickle.
Every time when oxygen is removed, the cells sickle.
And then they quickly desickle.
And they sickle and desickle and sickle and desickle
every time they run through the microcirculation.
And this then is going to result in one of the important complications of sickle cell anemia,
which is that there's going to be membrane damage to the red blood cell.
So imagine that if every time the cell sickles,
the sort of the crystals are pricking away at the membrane,
then over time that's going to result in membrane damage to the red blood cell.
And one of the major principles of clinical findings in sickle cell anemia
is actually related to membrane damage.
For example, because there's membrane damage,
the cells are going to become less flexible over time.
And as they become less flexible over time,
the spleen will actually remove them from the circulation.
And so that's going to result in extravascular hemolysis with an anemia.
At the same time, all of the consequences of extravascular hemolysis,
jaundice, as I've already explained, unconjugated hyperbilirubinemia,
and increased risk for bilirubin gallstones
will all be a consequence of extravascular hemolysis.
At the same time, some of the cells that are present in the blood
will actually lyse because the red cell membrane is being damaged.
That minimal amount, it's not the predominant mechanism of anemia,
but there is a decent amount of intravascular hemolysis
enough to decrease the serum heptoglobin.
So remember that heptoglobin is a scavenger molecule,
that when there is free hemoglobin in the blood,
the heptoglobin is the first molecule that tries to save that hemoglobin,
and so heptoglobin will actually decrease
because it will be used up as the intravascular hemolysis occurs.
At the same time, there will be target cells on the blood smear.
Why are there target cells on the blood smear?
These cells, as the membrane gets damaged, they begin to dehydrate.
And as they begin to dehydrate, the cytoplasm is going to be slowly decreased within those cells.
So, as I've already explained previously, but I'll explain one more time,
if this is the biconcave red blood cell and you begin to pull away cytoplasm,
there's going to be extra membrane.
There's going to be redundancy in the membrane.
It's like taking air out of a basketball.
And so, a little bleb can actually form here and here,
which would be full of hemoglobin,
which would then produce a red color both at the edges and in the center of the red blood cell.
And again, that's a target cell, and I've explained that previously as well.
Now, another consequence of the both intra- and extravascular hemolysis
is that there's going to be massive erythroid hyperplasia.
The bone marrow will undergo hyperplasia,
trying to produce as many red cells as possible.
This will result of expansion of hematopoiesis into the skull and facial bones.
When it goes into the skull, you're going to get a classic crew cut appearance on x-ray.
And when it goes into the facial bones,
it's going to create that classic chipmunk facies that we've talked about in beta-thal major.
Similarly, the patients will have extramedullary hematopoiesis with hepatomegaly,
and that's because once the bone marrow is completely full of hematopoiesis,
the next place that we could actually develop hematopoiesis would be extramedullary,
for example, in the spleen and in the liver.
However, these patients usually don't have a spleen, as I'm going to talk about later,
so it's predominantly in the liver.
There's also going to be a risk of aplastic crisis with parvovirus B19.
Again, we've already talked about that,
so these discussions now are becoming easier as you're more familiar with some of the themes
that apply to red blood cells.
Another consequence of sickling is that eventually you can develop irreversible sickling,
and so this is sort of the second major problem.
One problem was red blood cell damage,
which then resulted in the anemia and all of those complications I've already discussed.
A second major problem is irreversible sickling.
The irreversible sickling leads to vasoocclusion,
and vasoocclusion can then result in infarction of tissues.
The first classic example of vasoocclusion would be dactylitis.
Dactylitis refers to swelling of the bones of the hands and the feet,
usually due to vasoocclusive infarction.
This is the common presenting sign in infants, a very common presenting sign.
Examiners like to show you pictures in which they have pictures of swollen fingers
and hands of usually an African-American infant,
and then a classic vignette of sickle cell anemia,
and then you'll have to recognize that the patient has sickle cell anemia
or have to identify some derivative principle about sickle cell anemia.
So dactylitis is very high yield to be familiar with.
Again, classically seen in a six-month-old infant
as it is a common presenting sign of sickle cell anemia.
Additionally, because they get vasoocclusive crises in the spleen,
eventually the spleen gets infarcted and disappears.
That's called autosplenectomy.
It results in a shrunken fibrotic spleen.
Loss of the spleen then results in a series of problems.
Number one, if the spleen is no longer present,
the primary source of antibody production, which is the spleen, is lost,
and there's going to be an increased risk of infection with encapsulated organisms.
For example, H. flu, strep pneumo,
and this is very important because it's the most common cause of death
in children with sickle cell disease.
So it's very important to vaccinate these kids against the bugs
that they're most likely to be infected with.
That's one complication of autosplenectomy.
A second complication of autosplenectomy is an increased risk of salmonella osteomyelitis.
And whereas the most common cause of osteomyelitis overall is staph aureus,
in patients with sickle cell, the most common cause is salmonella.
And then the third consequence of autosplenectomy is how well jolly bodies on blood smear.
I've already explained this to you.
Red blood cells normally remove the entire nucleus.
However, in some cases, the nucleus may not be completely removed,
and it's the job of the spleen to go in and remove that little extra bit of nuclear material.
If the spleen is not present or not functional,
that extra material will remain in the rare red blood cell where it actually was present,
and that's called a how well jolly body.
And I've already explained this just a few moments ago as well.
Additionally, vaso-occlusive crises can occur within the vessels of the lung,
and that's called acute chest syndrome, vaso-occlusion in pulmonary microcirculation.
Classically presents with chest pain, shortness of breath, and infiltrates on the lung.
It's usually precipitated by pneumonia.
Now, the idea here is that the patient gets a lung infection,
and when they get a lung infection, the lung infection then causes vasodilation
and causes the blood flow to slow down a little bit,
and the slowing down of the blood flow increases the transit time for the red blood cells,
and an increased transit time can increase dehydration, can increase acidemia,
can also increase the deoxygenation of the red blood cells,
which would then promote sickling.
So this is the classic finding.
The patient gets a pneumonia, and then after the pneumonia,
they develop an acute chest syndrome.
Important to note because this is the most common cause of death in adults.
So in summary, what I would say is that the presenting sign is dactylitis.
The most common cause of death in kids is going to be infection with encapsulated organisms,
and the most common cause of death in adults is actually acute chest syndrome.
Vaso-occlusion can also result in pain crises,
for example, in other bones, in other organs, in other tissues.
You can get a vaso-occlusive crisis in the kidney,
and that can result in renal papillary necrosis,
and the classic finding in renal papillary necrosis is gross hematuria and proteinuria.
And so these are all complications of vaso-occlusive crises.
Now, of course, sickle cell is a very complicated disease,
and we could discuss many, many more findings,
but this is sort of the take-home paradigm that you need to bury away in your mind.
If a patient only has one mutated beta gene, then we call that sickle cell trait.
And you'll have to go back and remember that we've got two beta genes,
and this is beta-s, and this is beta, the normal beta.
So this patient has one mutated gene and one normal gene.
Now, when they make this beta, they're going to make beta-2 tetramers that are normal,
and when they make this beta, they're going to make beta-2 tetramers that are sickle,
and, of course, alpha-2 will join here, and alpha-2 will join here,
and so these patients will produce both hemoglobin A,
this is hemoglobin A,
and they'll also produce hemoglobin S.
So now they're producing both hemoglobins.
What's important to note here is that the production of beta
is a little more efficient than the production of beta-S,
and so they'll actually get, like, for example, 55% hemoglobin A
and maybe 45% hemoglobin S.
Again, what's important to note is that they're going to have less than 50% hemoglobin S.
Why am I highlighting that?
Because you need about 50% of hemoglobin S to actually sickle,
and if the patients have less than 50% hemoglobin S, they won't sickle.
So generally, these patients who have sickle cell trait are going to be asymptomatic.
That's because red blood cells with less than 50% hemoglobin S don't usually sickle in vivo.
There is one exception, however, and that's the renal medulla.
In the renal medulla, there's extreme hypoxia and hypertonicity,
and that extreme hypoxia and hypertonicity results in sickling.
The patients get microinfarctions.
Initially, it presents with microscopic hematuria.
Eventually, the classic finding is a decreased ability to concentrate the urine.
All of that is high yield concerning sickle cell trait.
Generally speaking, whether we're talking about sickle cell anemia or sickle cell trait,
it's important to note some basic laboratory findings.
Sickle cells and target cells would be seen in sickle cell disease, but not in trait.
And you know that, because in trait, the patients don't sickle,
so we wouldn't normally see sickling red blood cells on a smear.
However, were we to take metabisulfite, which is a chemical that can induce cells to sickle,
then if there is any degree of hemoglobin S, whether it be 50% or less than 50%,
it will cause the cell to sickle.
So otherwise stated, a metabisulfite screen allows you to identify hemoglobin S in any cell.
Therefore, it's positive in both disease and trait.
So it's a nice screening test if you're worried about sickle cell trait, for example.
Hemoglobin electrophoresis can also be useful to confirm the presence of hemoglobin S
and exactly how much there is.
So, for example, in disease, we know that the vast majority of hemoglobin will be hemoglobin S,
and then there will be some F and some A2.
But there will be no A, because there is no normal beta chain.
Remember, hemoglobin A is really composed of alpha 2 and beta 2,
and these patients don't have any normal beta 2.
In trait, there will be hemoglobin A, because they do have one normal beta gene.
And it will be about 55%.
There will be hemoglobin S, which will be less than 50%, and then a little bit of A2.
So this is important, again, but I've already highlighted some of this in our previous discussions.
Another important hemoglobinopathy to be familiar with is hemoglobin C.
Now, the problem here is that you have an autosomal recessive mutation, again, in the beta chain of hemoglobin,
but the normal glutamic acid, instead of being replaced by valine, as we had in sickle cell disease,
is replaced by lysine.
So that's the first point, is that hemoglobin C has lysine.
Hemoglobin C has lysine.
Maybe that might help you.
This is less common than sickle cell disease.
It presents with a mild anemia.
The anemia is predominantly due to extravascular hemolysis.
But what's most important about this disease, especially for examination purposes,
is that you characteristically see hemoglobin C crystals on the blood smear.
And this is the classic hemoglobin C crystal.
So lysine and hemoglobin C crystals.
That concludes our discussion of normocytic anemias with mostly extravascular hemolysis.
And our next discussion is going to be normocytic anemias with mostly extravascular hemolysis.